Continuing on a theme of routing, in this
lecture, I'm going to be telling you about
something called the Spanning Tree
Protocol.
The Spanning Tree Protocol is actually
used for Ethernet switches.
We normally think of routing as operating
at the, at the, at the IP or the network
layer.
But, anything that, any situation where we
want to send packets along a particular
path, path that we choose carefully, we
can think of that as routing.
So, Ethernet switches need to decide how
to route or forward packets to the correct
set of destinations as well.
So, that's what we're going to be looking
at in this video.
So, we're going to continue with this
theme of routing.
And I'm going to describe something that,
at first, won't seem like routing because
we normally use the term routing to refer
to the network layer and, and IP, IP
addressing.
But, routing really means any mechanism
for delivering packets in a, in a mindful
way from a source to a destination.
And so, in that sense, Ethernet routes
packets, too. It's forwarding packets from
a source to a destination, it just happens
to be doing this based on the Ethernet
address.
So, in this video, I'm going to be talking
about how Ethernet forwards packets.
So we know how addresses are learned in
Ethernet.
And, but, but how does it prevent loops
from happening?
It we, we know that it will learn the
address and until it's learned the address
and knows the correct direction to send
the packet, it will flood to everyone.
How do we make sure that those flooded
messages, those protocol messages are not
are not looping in the network forever?
After all, there's no TTL field in the
Ethernet.
So, Ethernet does this by building a
spanning tree over which packets are
forward, forwarded.
And, we're going to see that,
specifically, in a moment, this works in
quite a different way from the from what
we've seen so far.
Because instead of building a spanning
tree per destination or per, per router,
In Ethernet we're going to build a single
spanning tree for the entire network.
In other words, it's going to constrain
the overall topology to only use those
ports belonging to a single spanning tree.
So, just recall briefly how an Ethernet
switch forwards packets.
First of all, it examines the header of
each arriving Ethernet frame.
If it finds that the Ethernet destination
address is in its forwarding table, it's
going to forward the frame to the correct
outgoing port.
If the Ethernet destination address is not
found in the table, it's going to
broadcast the frame to all out going ports
because it doesn't know which one to send
it to, it's just going to send it to every
one.
And, now we've learned about flooding we
can see why it would do that we can be
sure it will reach it's eventual
destination.
And then, it learns entries in the table
are learned by examining the Ethernet
source address of arriving packets.
In other words, when it looks at the
source address, it will learn that in
order to reach that particular source
address,
It sends packets out through the port
through which that packet arrived, so that
must be on the direction between towards
the source.
But, this all presupposes that packets
don't loop in the network forever. And
that, in fact, the,
The, particularly in the learning process,
that the Ethernet source address actually
is on the shortest path or on a reasonable
path back towards that address.
So, how does it, how does it know that?
And, in fact, the whole learning process
could lead to loops.
So, let's see an example of, of what might
happen.
If we have a network with ah,, let's say,
this is source and a destination, and in
between we have a sequence of switches,
something like this, that are all
connected like, like this.
So, B is then directly connected here, and
then A is connected to a switch here.
In the learning processes, as we've
described, the first time that A sends to
B, and let's say it's going to send it's
going to send its packet in here destined
to B.
This first switch is not going to know
where to send it because it's never heard
from A and B, about A and B before. So,
it's going to flood its message out all
of these ports. That's going to come down
here.
It's going to, to go out here.
It's going to, to come down here. But,
because this what this switch here will do
is send it out of all the ports except the
one that it learnt, that it heard from,
This is also going to come from here back
down here, and go around this loop
forever. And this one is going to go
around this loop forever,
And there's another loop here. And so, you
can quickly get the picture.,
These packets are going to be looping
around forever.
They are going to get delivered to B.
B will respond and the address will get
learned.
But, in the meantime, we've created this
huge loop of flooded addresses.
So, we need to make sure that doesn't
happen.
The Spanning Tree Protocol that I'm going
to describe now was invented to solve this
problem.
So, rather than deciding how we route
along a spanning tree for, for each
address, or to reach each destination,
it's going to, to build one spanning tree
for the entire network.
So,
Just to give you an example, I'm going to
redraw my, or, a, a switch, network here
that has a bunch of loops in it.
Won't be exactly the same as the one
before, but roughly the same.
So, here with A and B.
What it's going to do is it's going to go
through and disable some ports in, in the
network to prevent this loop from
happening.
So, one example of what it might do is,
essentially switch off this link here so
that loop at the top is prevented.
And, it could switch off the loop, the,
the, the link here and prevent this loop
down, down here.
So we end up with a, a spanning tree in
this case which is like this of which all
the switches are on that spanning tree so
it spans.
It's a tree so that there are no loops.
And, A and B can talk to each other over
that spanning, over that spanning tree.
So, it gives us a rough idea of what we're
going to see next.
So, preventing loops.
The Spanning Tree Protocol, it's, it's
going to start by recognizing that the
topology of switches is a graph,
And we've seen many examples of these
before.
And, the Spanning Tree Protocol is going
to find a subgraph that spans all of the
vertices, all of the switches without
creating any loops,
It's a spanning tree.
And the distributed protocol is going to
run across all of these switches,
And it's going to start by deciding which
switch is the root of the tree, of the
single spanning tree that it's going to
create.
And then, which ports are allowed to
forward packets along the tree.
Let's look at an example here.
This is a, a just an example spanning
tree.
So, the step one is it's going to pick a
single a single root.
And the way that it's going to do this is,
just exchange ID numbers and pick the one
with the lowest ID.
So, I'm just going to assume here that
it's, it's exchanged enough to decide that
S1 is the root.
And then, it's going to forward packets on
the ports on the shortest hop count path
to the root.
And so, S6 would send along here, S2 would
send along here,
S4, we've seen many examples of this now
of how to create this.
S8, well, there's an up count of two here
and an up count of two here that's, that's
somewhat arbitrarily design that it's
going to send this way.
And then S3 that's got an hop count this
two this way and one, two, three this way
so it will send this way.
S9 will send this way.
So, there's a spending tree that covers
all of then.
And here's another one that, that, that
could be created.
It's, it's almost the same as the one
previously because it had a couple of ties
that I could break.
So, this is the logical spanning tree that
has been created. And, of course, there
are no loops in it and it spans all of the
switches.
So, the thing that remains to do is to
figure out, how it does this?
We know what it's going to end up with, so
how does it get there?
So, let's take a look at how Spanning Tree
Protocol works.
There's a little bit of detail here and
I'm going to, to go through this one step
at a time.
So, the first thing that happens is that
all switches broad, broadcast a special
type of packet called a Bridge Protocol
Data Unit.
Protocol Data Unit is just a little bit of
an old fashioned term for a Packet, and
Bridge is an older name for Switches
before Ethernet switches were popularized
in the 1990's they were called bridges.
So, Bridge Protocol Data Unit is usually
abbreviated to BPDU.
This isn't in the context in which this
term BPDU is, is used, so don't worry too
much about it.
It's essentially the special control
messages that are sent around, in order to
build the spanning tree.
The BPDU contains three pieces of
information.
The ID of who it is that's sending it, and
that's the, the switch ID.
So, in my previous example, S1, S2, S3,
it's usually actually derived from the MAC
address just so that it's unique and it
may be manually configured by the, by the
administrator. But, we'll just use the
switch IDs on, on the PowerPoint pictures
for now.
It contains the ID of who it currently
believes to be the root,
And we'll see how this evolves, in a
moment.
And, it's the distance from the sender to
the root.
In other words, what it believes is the
distance from itself to the root.
And this is the, the best, the best,
estimate that it has right now.
So, to start with, every switch is going
to, is going to boot up and think that
it's the root.
It's going to claim that it's the root.
In other words, it's going to put it's
idea of it's sender to be the same as the
idea of the root, and because they are one
and the same, it's going to say the
distance field to zero because that's the
distance from the sender to the root.
And every switch is going to broadcast
this value until it hears a better value.
In other words, a root with a smaller ID
would be the most likely case.
So, if I'm currently advertising that I
think that I'm root and then somebody else
sends me a message and says, I'm the root
and its ID is lower than mine, then I will
start saying, okay, I believe that you're
the root instead of me.
If there happens to be a root with the
same ID, it's going to pick the one with
the shorter distance and ties are going to
be broken by the smaller ID of the, of the
sender.
So, if a switch hears a better message,
it's not only going to adopt to that value
as the root, it's going to re-transmit
that message and it's going to add one to
the distance.
And say, I'm going to forward my ID as the
sender, the newly learned ID of the root,
And I'm going to go add with one value,
one to the value that was told to me
because the hop count is now increased by
one,
And I'm going to say that, that is the
distance from the sender to the root.
So eventually, jumping down to here.
Eventually, there will be only one root
that will originate this message and
everybody else will retransmit them.
Because everybody will uniquely pick the
same the same switch ID as the root.
Okay.
Now, we know who the root is.
We now have to figure out how this spanning
tree is built in order to send packets to
and from that root.
So, the root port is, is picked on every
switch.
It's the port on a switch that is closest
to the root.
In other words, its the one through which
the BPDU was heard, the talk, the gate
that was that shortest distance to the
root,
So that's nice and easy thing to figure
out.
And that will be the one through which it
sends messages, forwards messages to the
root or receives them from the root.
Not only the BPDUs but also the forwarded
packets.
The second type of port is what's called
the designated port.
This is the port that neighbors agree to
use in order to reach the port.
It's essentially the port through which
eventually packets had destined to the
root, root will be received at this
switch.
And packets coming from the root will be
forwarded onto this, onto this port in
order to reach the other switches.
All other ports are blocked from
forwarding.
In other words, only those ports that are
the root ports or the designated ports
will continue to forward regular packets.
All other ports are blocked from
forwarding.
However, they will still send and receive
BPDUs so that the control messages are
still send and receive so that we can
continue to build the spanning tree such
that if something changes, a switch goes
down or a link goes down, everybody will
converge on a new shortest, a new spanning
tree.
Okay. So eventually, locally, only, only
switch will only forward on the ports that
are root ports and designated ports.
Let me finish this video on the Spanning
Tree Protocol by telling you about a brief
history.
Spanning Tree Protocol was originally
invented in 1985 by Radia Perlman.
At that time Ethernet switches were called
bridges and networks were beginning to be
built with a large number of bridges.
This was really before routing was, was
very popular.
And as a consequence, they really needed a
quick method for, for reliably building a
spanning tree that all of the packets
coul, could follow to, to prevent
broadcast storms from escalating in the
network.
It was standardized in 1990 by IEEE.
Still yet, we converged relatively slowly
and this networks became bigger, this
became more and more of a problem.
The timers that we used were quite long
and the, the, the method takes quite a
while to converge.
And so, a more rapid version called the
Rapid Spanning Tree Protocol was
introduced in 2004.
Still, this built a single tree for the
entire network and the, the path followed
by the packets would often be a some what
torturous path, it's not necessarily the
shortest path between the source and
destination because these packets would
always have to go through the roots.
So, more recently, the Shortest Path
Bridging Protocol was introduced just in
2012, and this uses our old friend, the
link state algorithm.
A little bit like Dijkstra's algorithm
used in OSPF.
In order to build a shortest path tree,
from each source to each destination.
And so, in, in, in the end, we've ended up
with a method that is very similar to
what's used at, at layer three.
This will probably be rolled out and
adopted over the next few years.
That's the end of this video.